<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The incomprehensibleness of God in a sermon preached before Their Majesties at White-Hall, Decemb. 31 1693 / by Richard Lucas ...</title>
            <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26318</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12579329</idno>
  <idno type="VID">200324</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240971082</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3401</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12579329</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 200324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 965:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The incomprehensibleness of God in a sermon preached before Their Majesties at White-Hall, Decemb. 31 1693 / by Richard Lucas ...</title>
                  <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Smith, and B. Walford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">God --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:200324:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:200324:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Incomprehensibleness of God,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preached before Their MAJESTIES, AT <hi>WHITE-HALL, Decemb.</hi> 31. 1693.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Lucas,</hi> D. D. Vicar of S. <hi>Stephen's Colemanstreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Their Majesties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>S. Smith,</hi> and <hi>B. Walford,</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in <hi>S. Paul's</hi> Church-Yard. 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:200324:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:200324:2"/>
            <head>The Incomprehensibleness of God.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB XI. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Canst thou by searching find out God? Canst thou find out the Almighty unto Perfection?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>JOB</hi> in the foregoing Chapter, carried the Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his Integrity so far, that he seem'd to entrench somewhat rudely on <hi>the Justice of Providence; Zophar</hi> therefore to repress this Insolence, and vindicate the Divine Honor, lays be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him the <hi>Incomprehensibleness</hi> and <hi>Majesty of God.</hi> That this is a proper Topick to awe the Rashness, and to chastise the Pride of Man, is evident from hence, that God himself makes use of it to this End, Chap. 38. <hi>Then God answered Job out of the whirlwind, and said, who is this that darkeneth Counsel by words without knowledge? where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if ever it were necessary to possess our Minds with a due Sense of the <hi>Meaness of Man,</hi> and the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:200324:3"/>
               <hi>Majesty of God,</hi> 'tis now; now, when Luxury and Hypocrisie, Loosness and Corruption do not more openly insult and affront the <hi>Morals,</hi> than Atheism and Infidelity the <hi>Faith</hi> of Christianity; now, when <hi>Scepticism, Heresie</hi> and <hi>Impiety</hi> assault our Religion with all the Artillery of <hi>Judaism, Arrianism, Photini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anism, Turcism:</hi> now, when bold Men trample under foot all <hi>Mysteries,</hi> and under colour of advancing <hi>free and impartial Reason,</hi> do in effect cashier <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Never therefore was it more necessary than <hi>now</hi> to put the Question in my Text, and to invite the World to consider the Consequences naturally flowing from it. 'Tis a <hi>Question</hi> which implies its own <hi>Answer, Canst thou by searching find out God? Canst thou find out the Almighty unto perfection?</hi> i. e. 'Tis past all Controversie thou canst not. The Sense then of the Words is easily resolved into this Proposition: <hi>That God is incomprehensible.</hi> I will therefore,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Assert and illustrate this Doctrine in my Text, and then</item>
               <item>2. Make two or three Inferences from it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That God is incomprehensible.</hi> This is an <hi>Article of the Athanasian Creed;</hi> and if <hi>universal Tradition</hi> may be allowed to weigh any thing, there is no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in our Religion can lay a fairer Claim to it; but it needs derive no Strength from <hi>Human Authority,</hi> being asserted in almost so many Words in my Text,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:200324:3"/>and either in express Terms, or immediate, necessary, and obvious Consequence, in innumerable others; and I think all Men who have not abandon'd their <hi>Modesty,</hi> with their <hi>Faith,</hi> must confess, that with respect to <hi>human Capacity, infinite</hi> and <hi>incomprehensible</hi> are Terms almost equivalent, and consequently who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever attributes the <hi>one</hi> to God must be obliged not to deny the <hi>other.</hi> All this being clear, I shall not so much labour to prove, as to illustrate, and unfold this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>The Heathens painted their <hi>Demiurgus,</hi> to whom they assign'd Eternity, for a Companion in pitchy Darkness, retired within a Cave, which their Poets thus describe:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Est ignota procul mentique impervia nostrae</l>
               <l>Vix adeunda Diis —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Not intimating by this, that they had no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge at all of God amongst 'em, but that the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Divine Nature,</hi> were too vast, too high, too deep, what shall I say, <hi>too mysterious</hi> for human Minds, nay for Angels to search out. 'Twas this Notion made the Philosopher exact so much <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> in all Discourses on Divine Things, which <hi>Seneca</hi> commends as a wise and great Thought.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:200324:4"/>
            <p>Now all this was probably borrowed from <hi>Moses</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> how near soever God was to <hi>Israel,</hi> yet would not he endure that they should approach too near <hi>to Mount Sinai</hi> to <hi>gaze, Exodus</hi> xix. 21. And how <hi>familiarly</hi> soever God would be consulted by <hi>Moses,</hi> yet when he desired <hi>to see his Glory,</hi> Chap. 33. <hi>God said unto him,</hi> Verse 20. <hi>thou canst not see my face.</hi> And <hi>Verse</hi> 23. <hi>Thou shalt see my back-parts, but my face shall not be seen.</hi> To the same purpose is that of the <hi>Prophet, Verily thou art a God that hidest thy self, O God of Israel our Saviour,</hi> Isai. xlv. 15. and that of <hi>Solomon, the Lord said that he would dwell in the thick darkness,</hi> 1 Kings viii. 12. Under the <hi>Gospel</hi> indeed the Son of God is said to have <hi>revealed God to us,</hi> John 1.18. but yet even this <hi>Revelation</hi> must not be supposed to have exhausted <hi>all the Depths</hi> and <hi>Mysteries</hi> of the <hi>God-head;</hi> for notwithstanding this <hi>Revelation,</hi> we as yet <hi>see but as thorough a Glass darkly, we know but in part, and prophesie in part,</hi> 1 Cor. xiii. 9. He is reveal'd to us, as he was in the Pillar of Cloud and Fire to <hi>Israel,</hi> to <hi>guide our feet</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> not to <hi>entertain our Curiosity;</hi> that is, he is sufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in order to <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> but no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for in all other Respects, if under the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament,</hi> he made <hi>Darkness his Pavilion,</hi> under the <hi>New,</hi> he <hi>dwells in Light inaccessible.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:200324:4"/>
            <p>To advance to <hi>Particulars;</hi> If in the <hi>God-head</hi> we <hi>gaze</hi> and <hi>pry</hi> too boldly into <hi>eternal Generation</hi> and <hi>Procession,</hi> and the <hi>ineffable Unity of Father, Son, and Holy Ghost,</hi> it will but dazle and confound our weak Faculties; as far as the Scripture is plain, we may, and must advance, namely, that <hi>the Father is God, the Son is God,</hi> and <hi>the Holy Ghost is God,</hi> and <hi>yet there are not three Gods, but one God;</hi> if we content not our selves here, without a <hi>Philosophical</hi> Account of the <hi>mysterious</hi> and <hi>inexplicable Unity</hi> and Distinction of <hi>Father, Son</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> we shall be more like to lose our selves than find out an <hi>incomprehensible Truth.</hi> All human Explications, as far as ever I could observe yet, do but breed new Doubts and Scruples, not dissipate the old.</p>
            <p>If we enquire after the <hi>Substance</hi> or <hi>Essence</hi> of God, we are told indeed, <hi>John</hi> iv. 24. <hi>That he is a Spirit,</hi> and so are <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Souls:</hi> but what vast Distance there is between that <hi>Self-Existent,</hi> and these <hi>created Spirits;</hi> alas, what <hi>human Understanding</hi> can comprehend? When we speak but of <hi>created Spirits,</hi> how little is it that we know of <hi>them?</hi> We learn indeed from the Operations of our own Minds, that <hi>Thinking</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> belong to <hi>Spirits,</hi> but all our Attempts beyond this, look little better than inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Guesses, and fancyful Amusements. The most subtil Discourses on this Subject, seeming to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:200324:5"/>me to amount to but this at most, that we rather understand <hi>what Spirits are not, than what they are.</hi> A <hi>Spirit,</hi> 'tis true, <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> tell us, <hi>has not Flesh and Bones,</hi> is not made of the same <hi>Stuff with our mortal Bodies,</hi> Luke xxiv. 39. But if we demand what the <hi>Substance</hi> of it is, alas, we can form no <hi>Idea</hi> of this; our Fancy gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, and cannot raise it self above this visible World, above <hi>Matter,</hi> above <hi>Body,</hi> above some <hi>pure Ethereal Substance,</hi> or something of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I know not what, which is but a little better Account of this Matter, for ought I know, than <hi>Homer</hi>'s and <hi>Epicurus</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it were Flesh, and as it were Blood.</p>
            <p>Let us now come to the <hi>Attributes</hi> of God. Here not to mention, that the very Distinction between <hi>Essence</hi> and <hi>Attributes,</hi> is meer Condescension to the Weakness of <hi>human Capacity;</hi> that it is as difficult to conceive <hi>both</hi> to be the <hi>very same simple thing,</hi> as it is repugnant to <hi>Reason</hi> to <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>separate</hi> them. Not I say to mention this, the <hi>Attributes</hi> of God, as they have their <hi>bright</hi> side, so have they their <hi>dark</hi> one too; as far as God has revealed, we stand upon sure and safe Ground, but beyond this we know not where we tread; for if we go about to frame our Notions of <hi>boundless Perfections,</hi> from some faint Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblances of them in <hi>created Beings,</hi> and to judge of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:200324:5"/>God by the actings and movings of our own Minds in these Bodies of Clay, we must needs fall vastly beneath any just and commensurate <hi>Idea</hi> of Divine Excellencies; and yet this is the highest, this is the utmost Effort of Reason.</p>
            <p>All the <hi>Attributes</hi> of God are <hi>infinite</hi> in their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> and whosoever goes about to fathom what is <hi>infinite,</hi> is guilty of the Folly of that Country-man in the <hi>Poet,</hi> who sitting on the Bank-side, expects to see the Stream run quite away, and leave its Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel dry; but that runs on and will do so to all Ages. Thus he that goes about to frame to himself an adequate Notion of <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> and <hi>Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,</hi> cannot but attempt the Contradiction of limiting the <hi>one,</hi> and manacling the <hi>other.</hi> The Mind which travels in the Contemplation of <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> loseth its self in the Journey, like an <hi>Eye,</hi> which if it meet with nothing to intercept its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, its <hi>Quickness</hi> doth not find an End, but its <hi>Weakness</hi> makes one.</p>
            <p>If we proceed to God's <hi>Moral Attributes,</hi> 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that as much as is revealed of them, we do, or may understand aright; but if we fancy we can <hi>comprehend</hi> the whole Extent of them, we do but <hi>deceive</hi> our selves; for <hi>Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> as well as <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Duration</hi> are <hi>infinite</hi> when ascribed to God and therefore tho our <hi>Moral Hahits</hi> have so much,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:200324:6"/>Resemblance of these <hi>Divine Attributes,</hi> that the <hi>Spirit</hi> stiles them the <hi>Image of God,</hi> Col. iii. 10. and a <hi>Participation of the Divine Nature.</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. Yet does the <hi>same Spirit,</hi> with respect to the <hi>Infiniteness</hi> of God's <hi>Moral Perfections,</hi> assert that there are <hi>none good,</hi> Luke xviii. 19. <hi>None wise but God,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.17. In a word, all Men that think <hi>soberly,</hi> however taught that the best way of defining or describing the <hi>Perfections of God,</hi> is by excluding and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from him all the Defects and Imperfections of his Creatures; which is the same thing as if we should say of every <hi>Divine Attribute,</hi> that it has in it all the <hi>Perfection</hi> we can possibly conceive, and <hi>infinitely more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sum of all is this, Tho God were so far discoverable by the <hi>Light of Reason,</hi> as served to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Idolatry and Wickedness of the <hi>Pagan World</hi> unexcusable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. tho he were revealed to the <hi>Jew,</hi> and more fully to us under the <hi>Gospel,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct us in the Nature of Religious Worship, and our Obligations to it, yet still God being <hi>infinite,</hi> and his <hi>Perfections</hi> a vast Abyss, there are therefore <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries in the God-head,</hi> which <hi>human Reason</hi> cannot penetrate, <hi>Heights</hi> which we cannot soar, and <hi>Reason</hi> it self, if it be not <hi>drunk with Pride and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance,</hi> will not only acknowledge that it is thus, but also that it is fit it should be thus; for, if Man
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:200324:6"/>could <hi>fully comprehend God,</hi> how <hi>Great</hi> must we be, how <hi>little</hi> He, we more than Men, He less than God. When the <hi>Prophet</hi> tells us, <hi>that all the Nations upon Earth, in Comparison of him, are but as the drop of the Bucket, or the Grain of the Ballance,</hi> Isai. xl. and by a clear Consequence all the <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Understanding</hi> upon Earth, if <hi>united in one Man,</hi> can be but as a <hi>little Particle of Light</hi> to that <hi>eternal Sun,</hi> a <hi>Drop</hi> to that <hi>eternal, boundless, and inexhaustible Fountain,</hi> how is it possible, that Man should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God!</p>
            <p>I will conclude my Reflections upon this <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition</hi> in the Words of <hi>Zophar,</hi> close after my Text, <hi>Vers.</hi> 8.9. <hi>It is as high as Heaven, what canst thou do? deeper than Hell, what canst thou know? The Measure thereof is longer than the Earth, and broader than the Sea.</hi> Having thus open'd and establish'd the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in my Text, <hi>That God is incomprehensible;</hi> I will now proceed to make <hi>Two or three Inferences</hi> from it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To let out the Tumor of Self-conceit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>To justifie our Belief of Mysteries.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>To vindicate the Doctrine of Providence.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Consideration of God's <hi>Incomprehensible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> should methinks <hi>humble</hi> Man, prevail with him to <hi>think soberly of himself,</hi> and to contain his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries after God, within <hi>sober</hi> and <hi>modest</hi> Bounds.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:200324:7"/>This is that <hi>Zophar</hi> seems to aim at, witness that sharp Reflection, <hi>Verse</hi> 12. <hi>Vain Man would be wise, tho Man be born like a wild Asses Colt.</hi> 'Tis obvious to us all, <hi>what</hi> Man is born, and 'tis as obvious, that he grows up into a rational Creature, by slow steps, repeated Instructions, and tedious Experience; and 'tis as evident, that in the height and maturity of his rational Attainments, the Soul how great soever it be in its self, is clogg'd by a lumpish Body, streighten'd by scanty Organs, clouded by Passions, and perverted by Prejudices, which always limit, and too too frequently misguide it, in its <hi>Enquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Truth.</hi> This being so, there cannot be a clearer Proof of Man's Folly, than his aptness to be <hi>puffed up</hi> with an Opinion of his Wisdom, nor can any thing more notoriously expose his Ignorance, than his extravagant Pretensions, to an unlimited and an universal Knowledge. What, nothing satisfie this poor Creature, but <hi>the comprehending or discarding Mysteries!</hi> What, can <hi>this Understanding,</hi> such as I have described it, be the <hi>Test</hi> and <hi>Standard of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Truth!</hi> Can this <hi>shallow Capacity</hi> measure the <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most</hi> Extent of Nature, and the God of it too! Alas, We may with as much <hi>Reason</hi> pretend to contain <hi>the Waters in the Hollow of our Hand,</hi> to <hi>mete out Heaven with a Span,</hi> and <hi>weigh the Mountains of the Earth in a pair of Scales!</hi> 'Tis true, we have <hi>Revelation,</hi> but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:200324:7"/>we ought never to forget that of S. <hi>Paul, When I was a Child, I thought as a Child, I spake as a Child;</hi> for in the <hi>brightest Revelations</hi> God talks with us in such Language, instructs and governs us by such Notions, as we in this <hi>our Childhood</hi> are capable of; our Language is that of Men, not Angels, and our Notions such as fit this <hi>State of Mortality,</hi> not one of <hi>Glory</hi> or <hi>Perfection.</hi> When ever therefore we go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout proudly to explicate a <hi>Mystery,</hi> as if it were indeed but <hi>an Idol,</hi> the Figment of Man's Brain, we serve it as the <hi>Ark of God</hi> did <hi>Dagon,</hi> cast it down from the height where it stood to the Earth, and leave it a maim'd and shapeless Trunk.</p>
            <p>But what talk I of our <hi>Comprehension of Divine Mysteries,</hi> when there is scarcely the most trifling Product of Nature, an <hi>Ant,</hi> a <hi>Fly,</hi> a <hi>Spire of Grass,</hi> that has not something or other in it that fools our Enquiry, and baffles our Confidence; how much more then the God of Nature who is concealed from us by the infinite Splendour of his inconceivable Glories, and retired within the Veil of his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible Excellencies and Perfections. Ah! let us then content our selves with <hi>admiring</hi> and <hi>loving</hi> that God, which we cannot yet at least <hi>comprehend.</hi> Let us imitate <hi>Elijah,</hi> who when God passed by, <hi>wrapt his Face in a Mantle,</hi> and stood at the Mouth of the Cave, to <hi>adore</hi> and <hi>worship,</hi> not gaze upon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:200324:8"/>his Majesty. Let us content our selves with such a Search after the Knowledge of God, as may sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and exalt our Minds, as may strengthen and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish our Obedience, and enkindle in us ardent Desires after that Heaven, wherein we shall no longer <hi>know in part,</hi> and <hi>see as thorough a Glass darkly,</hi> but we shall <hi>know as we are known,</hi> and <hi>see Face to Face.</hi> In the mean time,</p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Incomprehensibleness of God does abundantly justifie our Belief of Gospel-Mysteries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Mystery</hi> in the Notion of some at this Day, is indeed a very odd thing, that is, something of which we understand nothing at all, and from hence they fasten upon us those insulting Consequences, that we believe we know not what, and that we make Christ in revealing a Mystery to have revealed just nothing at all. Truly, whatever these Men pretend to, there is little Acuteness in this, What, is there no Difference between know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>all things,</hi> and knowing <hi>nothing,</hi> between a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>comprehensive Knowledge</hi> and <hi>utter Ignorance?</hi> Blessed be God, the meanest of our People have a better Notion of a <hi>Mystery,</hi> and 'tis this, <hi>That it is a Doctrine or Article, wherein much is revealed, and yet much hidden and abstruse;</hi> wherein there is something <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>intelligible,</hi> something <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>inscrutable,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:200324:8"/>something that we <hi>do</hi> or <hi>may know,</hi> something that we <hi>cannot.</hi> That there are such <hi>Mysteries</hi> in the Gospel, no Man ought to doubt, when <hi>S. Paul</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts, <hi>that we know but in part.</hi> Such a <hi>Mystery</hi> is God, as I have shew'd already, and such a <hi>Mystery</hi> is the <hi>Incarnation of our Lord.</hi> That the <hi>Word</hi> was <hi>made Man</hi> is <hi>reveal'd,</hi> and there is no <hi>Term</hi> in this Proposition but what is intelligible enough; but if we enquire into the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of that <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> wherein this <hi>Incarnation</hi> consists, this is to all of us a <hi>Mystery;</hi> and I wonder not if it seem a very contradictious one to a <hi>Socinian,</hi> whose <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Philosophy,</hi> if we may take his Word, are not able to furnish him with any higher Notion of <hi>Union</hi> than what results from <hi>Coextention of parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the Notion of a <hi>Mystery,</hi> to assert the Reasonableness of believing one, when revealed by God, is no more than to assert, that the <hi>Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensibleness</hi> of something involved and wrapt up in a <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> ought not to supplant our Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ef of that which is <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>intelligible.</hi> That <hi>secret things belong to God,</hi> but <hi>those that are revealed to us and our Children;</hi> That the <hi>Shallowness</hi> of human Capacity is no Objection against the <hi>Veracity</hi> of God, nor ought our <hi>Dimness</hi> or <hi>Dullness</hi> to invalidate or disparage <hi>Divine Authority;</hi> All this is plain of its self, and if it were not, may be made out by an
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:200324:9"/>answerable Arguments. To make <hi>Mysteries</hi> stoop and bow down to our Capacities, and if they will not, to reject them, is in effect to devest them of their Nature, and to make them none. Besides, what Grounds shall we proceed upon in such an Enquiry as this? Shall we judge of Divine Things by Maxims of <hi>Corpuscular Philosophy?</hi> How ridiculous and absurd were this? especially when the <hi>Philosophy</hi> of one Age overthrows that of another, and Time again rather confounds the <hi>Old,</hi> than esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishes the <hi>New.</hi> Indeed, in almost every days Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, something or other occurs to every modest Enquirer into Nature, too wonderful, and too big for our Capacities, so that we are forc'd, either to disbelieve the Evidence of our <hi>Sense,</hi> or to confess the Weakness of our <hi>Reason.</hi> Is it reasonable then to expect that the <hi>Mysteries of our Faith</hi> should be more easie and demonstrable than the <hi>Objects of our Sense?</hi> Or if not, yet, that that <hi>Reason</hi> which is so purblind, in the search of <hi>Natural,</hi> should be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judge of <hi>Divine Things?</hi> It is true, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve without a Reason for it, is <hi>Credulity,</hi> not <hi>Faith:</hi> But it is as true, that as the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> of God, is the Supreme Reason of our <hi>Obedience,</hi> so is his <hi>Veracity</hi> of our <hi>Faith.</hi> So that all that <hi>Reason</hi> can have to do here, is not to reject the <hi>Articles</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, because we cannot fathom all the <hi>Depths</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:200324:9"/>and Mystteries contain'd in them, but to examine the Authority and <hi>sense</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and these being once cleared, to Sacrifice all our doubts and Scruples to our <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this is most <hi>reasonable,</hi> so is it most <hi>safe</hi> too, and that upon two plain Grounds;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Because thus we worship God with our <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings</hi> as well as <hi>Wills,</hi> and captivate our <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> as well as our <hi>Affections</hi> to the <hi>Obedience of Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>. This will secure our <hi>Faith,</hi> and keep us from Apostatising thorough <hi>Pride</hi> or <hi>Confidence;</hi> whereas such as stumble at every thing in Scripture, which includes in it any thing <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>inscrutable,</hi> such who indulge to themselves such a <hi>liberty of Prophesy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as to forsake the received and obvious sence of Scripture, if it do not square with their <hi>Axioms</hi> or Rules of <hi>proud Reason.</hi> Such as these, have in all Ages miserably tortured and perverted the Scripture, and adulterated our holy Religion by <hi>sophistical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties</hi> and <hi>bold Fancies,</hi> devested it of every thing that is august and mysterious in it, debased our <hi>Faith</hi> into <hi>vain Philosophy,</hi> our <hi>Christianity</hi> into mere <hi>Paganism,</hi> divided the <hi>Church of Christ</hi> by innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Schisms,</hi> and multiplied bold and blasphemous <hi>Heresies</hi> from time to time. In a word if we will be Christians, <hi>the Reason of our faith must be resolved into the Veracity of God, not the Philosophy of Man;</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:200324:10"/>we must <hi>search the Scriptures,</hi> with the generous <hi>Bereans,</hi> to see <hi>whether these things be true or no;</hi> but must not stupidly or arrogantly put the Question of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> how <hi>can these things be?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>But does not this make way for <hi>Superstition</hi> and <hi>Error</hi> under pretence of <hi>Mystery?</hi> on the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; whoever forsakes the received, natural and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous sense of <hi>Scripture,</hi> as he has no warrant to expect the <hi>conduct</hi> and <hi>guidance of the Spirit,</hi> so has he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to fear that <hi>fancy</hi> may lead him to <hi>fatal Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pices.</hi> Besides that such a one ought to Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that wresting the words of Scripture by <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cism,</hi> or its sence by <hi>subtility</hi> or <hi>Sophistry</hi> is the next step to a down right <hi>rejecting its Authority.</hi> But must we then admit of a sence loaded with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions? by no means; But we must take Care, least while we Combat the <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Notions</hi> of Men, we carry on the War too far, and oppose and fight against the <hi>express sense</hi> and <hi>Mind of God.</hi> We must take Care too, in the next place, that we be not too forward to charge what is <hi>above our Reason</hi> with Contradictions, for this, if it be not it self a Contradiction to right Reason, is to Modesty and Ingenuity, for 'tis to pronounce of and censure what we do not understand.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:200324:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> The <hi>Incomprehensibleness of God solves all the Difficulties that clog the Doctrine of Providence.</hi> These must be acknowledg'd to be many. To make the <hi>actual Concourse</hi> or <hi>Super intendence</hi> of God, in every <hi>Folly or sinful Action,</hi> in every <hi>trifling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> or <hi>Blunder of Nature,</hi> to consist with his <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>Majesty;</hi> To reconcile <hi>Confusion</hi> and <hi>Disorder</hi> with <hi>unerring Wisdom,</hi> a thousand for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitous and blind <hi>Events</hi> with <hi>eternal</hi> and <hi>uncontrolable Counsel and Contrivance, Infallibility</hi> in <hi>Foreknowledge</hi> with <hi>Uncertainty in Events, Fate</hi> and <hi>Necessity</hi> in the <hi>End,</hi> with <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Contingency</hi> in the <hi>Means,</hi> this seems a very puzzling Undertaking, as to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miscuous Dispensation of Good and Evil, the wisest and best Men were sometimes at a Loss to reconcile this with the <hi>Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> of God. 'Tis true, a <hi>Judgment</hi> to come, solves this Difficulty, and it may be, <hi>Humility</hi> might have done so without it, since the best Men, what Evil soever they met with, have receiv'd more, and suffered less, than they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served. But it may be, it is more difficult to make this kind of Administration consist with God's Love and Zeal for Virtue, than with his Justice. Again, In our Notion of Perfection to do less good than one can, is a <hi>Defect</hi> at least, and yet if God had made all things at first, as <hi>perfect,</hi> or govern'd 'em since as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:200324:11"/>well as He could, whence is it, that the World is such as it is. But, if in <hi>temporal Things</hi> only, a <hi>blind and arbitrary Chance</hi> did seem to govern, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life might rectifie this, but what shall recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it in <hi>spiritual Things?</hi> That Grace should be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersed as unaccountably as temporal Favours, that the <hi>Manifestation of Jesus in the flesh,</hi> should be the only effectual Means to reclaim the World, and yet that He should make his Entrance into it so late, that untimely Death should surprize well inclined Persons in their first Debauches, and pious ones in their first Revolts and Relapses, when others despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and irrecoverably wicked, sin out Life to the last, fullest and ripest Period; For so much Sin to enter into a World of God's own Creation, and grow to such an Excess, if God had done all he could, to prevent or extirpate it, seems hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with his <hi>infinite Power</hi> and <hi>Wisdom,</hi> and yet for God to neglect any Means necessary to the Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Suppression of it, seems no less inconsistent with <hi>his Holiness;</hi> That the Almighty should fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see from all Eternity how small the Flock would be which should inherit Heaven, and how his wretched Creatures would throng in Crowds the <hi>broad way to destruction,</hi> and yet delight to <hi>Create</hi> a <hi>World,</hi> which was to be fill'd with so much Sin, and end in so
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200324:11"/>much Misery, seems very difficultly reconcileable with his <hi>Goodness,</hi> and yet that he should not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see all this is utterly inconsistent with his <hi>Perfection,</hi> and particularly his <hi>Foreknowledge.</hi> These and such like Difficulties, the <hi>Manichees</hi> endeavoured to solve by asserting <hi>two first Principles,</hi> an <hi>evil,</hi> and a <hi>good one,</hi> but with what success every Body knows; as to the success of others from time to time in the same Attempt, I'll pronounce nothing: This only I may affirm, that the <hi>Incomprehensibleness of God,</hi> is both a pious and a satisfactory Answer to these and all other Doubts of this Nature; It is enough to say with the Apostle, <hi>Rom.</hi> xi. . <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and knowledge of God, how unsearchable are his Judgments, and his ways past finding out!</hi> It is but Justice, that we should <hi>stifle our Doubts,</hi> and suspend our Censure of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, when we consider how far both <hi>his Counsels</hi> and <hi>his Actions</hi> are raised above our Enquiries. How can we, without the Guilt of Confidence and Rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, prescribe Rules to <hi>Power, Wisdom,</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> in their own Nature <hi>infinite?</hi> We know not where God began, nor where he will make an end; his <hi>Wisdom</hi> comprehends a thousand things we can never think of, and his Omnipotence can accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish ten thousand more, which we can never as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:200324:12"/>much as fancy possible. Past, present, and to come, form but one entire prospect to <hi>him;</hi> and tho things appear <hi>confused, scattered, mangled,</hi> and <hi>dismembered</hi> to us, to <hi>him</hi> they appear <hi>uniform, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> and <hi>Harmonious;</hi> we can therefore no more judge of the <hi>Wisdom, Justice,</hi> or <hi>Goodness</hi> of God, by any <hi>particular</hi> Instances of <hi>Providence</hi> disjoined from the whole, than we can of the Beauty and Spirit of a Poem by some shatter'd, confus'd and incoherent Fragments.</p>
            <p>The World, in a Word, is often wont and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to be compared to a <hi>well laid Dramatick Plot,</hi> which tho to the Spectator who beholds some part only, it seems ravell'd and intangl'd, yet to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who walks within the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of his own Scenes, the whole appears smooth and natural, and if you will have the patience to set it out to the <hi>last Act,</hi> it will appear so to us too. The <hi>Day</hi> is just ready to open, that will decipher all the <hi>Riddles of Divine Providence,</hi> unravel all the Intricacies, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold all the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of its elaborate Scenes, and we shall then see <hi>Perfection</hi> rising out of <hi>Corruption,</hi> like Light out of Darkness, <hi>Sin</hi> ending in <hi>Holiness,</hi> and the <hi>Miseries</hi> of all who do not willfully obstruct it in <hi>Happiness.</hi> In the mean time, our business is not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude our selves into the <hi>Counsels of God,</hi> to arraign the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:200324:12"/>Conduct which we do not understand; much less to <hi>reject a Providence,</hi> because we cannot discover the <hi>hidden Springs,</hi> trace the <hi>various Windings,</hi> and ken the <hi>distant Ends</hi> of it; But to adore the <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> which we cannot <hi>fathom,</hi> and with an humble awe <hi>magnifie</hi> and <hi>revere</hi> those <hi>Counsels</hi> which we cannot <hi>penetrate.</hi> Let us follow the Advice of <hi>Zophar,</hi> Vers. 1, 14 <hi>let us prepare our hearts and stretch out our hands towards God, if iniquity be in our hands let us put it far away, and let not Wickedness dwell in our Tabernacles.</hi> Then may we securely confide in God, and follow wheresoever <hi>his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> leads, and those Paths which appear to us like <hi>Labyrinths</hi> and <hi>Mazes,</hi> will yet prove our next way to our <hi>Canaan;</hi> for <hi>all things</hi> must and will <hi>work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good to them that love and fear God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have nothing more to do, but to convert my <hi>Exhortations</hi> into <hi>Prayers.</hi> May the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the <hi>Incomprehensible Mystery of God,</hi> increase our Veneration for our <hi>Holy Religion,</hi> and secure the Peace of our Bosoms against the Assaults of <hi>Profaness</hi> and <hi>Irreligion</hi> on the one hand, and of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Heresie</hi> on the other: May God fill our Souls with <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi> and may an <hi>awful Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>devout Humility</hi> guard and fortifie both: May the <hi>Spirit of Religion</hi> in all of us, never eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:200324:13"/>in <hi>giddy Novelties</hi> and <hi>daring Disputes,</hi> but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert itself in <hi>solid Virtues</hi> and <hi>great</hi> and <hi>good Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> May we all be inspired with a <hi>zeal</hi> for God, a zeal that may make us the <hi>great Examples</hi> as well as <hi>Assertors</hi> of our <hi>truly Catholick and Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith;</hi> a zeal that may effectually contribute to give a stop to the spreading Leprosie of <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Innovation,</hi> to root out <hi>Atheism</hi> and <hi>Wickedness,</hi> and to propagate <hi>Godliness in the power of it</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out these Realms. So shall that God who hath promised <hi>to honour those who honour him,</hi> be our strength and Glory, our Confidence and Boast all the day long; and when we have happily finished our Race, and bow down under no other weight than that of Years and of mortal Body, he shall translate us into the Presence of his Glory, where we shall find the <hi>Seraphin</hi> themselves praising that <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Zeal,</hi> which I invite you to here; for they are described in the Prophet to have <hi>two wings to cover their Eyes, two to cover their Feet, and two to fly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glory be to the Father and to the Son, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:200324:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>